Register of the Georges Albertini Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Georges Albertini papers,
1938-1986
80104
Albertini, Georges, 1911-1983
16 ms. boxes (6.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, and other writings, relating to political conditions in France, communism in France, international communism, and anti-communist movements.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Initally acquired in 1980.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1911 Born, Chalon-sur-Saône, France
1932 Joins the French Socialist Party
1942-1944 Secretary-General, Rassemblement Natonal Populaire
1944 Cabinet secretary for Marcel Dé, Minister of Labor in Vichy government Tried and sentenced for collaboration with German occupation
1945-1948 Imprisoned
1949 Meets Boris Souvarine, who becomes his associate
1949-1983 Edits and publishes the Bulletin d'études et d'informations politiques internationales, which in 1956 becomes Est-Ouest
1951 Amnestied by French government
1969-1974 Advisor to French president Georges Pompidou
1983 Died
Scope and Content Note
Acquired in 1967, with major increments received in 1980 and 1985, the Georges Albertini papers in the Hoover Institution Archives consist largely of Albertini's extensive files on French political life over three decades following World War II, with a major emphasis on the role of the French Communist Party during this period.
The principal biography of Albertini is entitled L'homme de l'ombre, or "the man of the shadows," and this seems an apt description of Albertini's role as a chronicler and confidant, a man operating in the corridors as an adviser to leading figures in the French establishment while pursuing a consistently anti-Communist agenda as the editor and publisher of his own political newsletter and journal.
Given his past as a collaborator with the German occupiers of France, activity for which he was tried and convicted, Albertini would at first glance seem to be an unlikely candidate for the role of political insider in postwar France. However, he emerged from prison with his connections to the French political elite largely intact, and with a clear conception of his part as purveyor of information on the French Communist Party to conservative and socialist opponents of the communists. Moreover, in choosing Boris Souvarine as his principal associate, Albertini benefited from Souvarine's intimate knowledge of the international communist movement, and the publication they produced, Est-Ouest, became a journal of reference for many in the French political class.
Throughout his life, Albertini kept meticulous records of his many meetings with French politicians, journalists, and businessmen. These can be found in the NOTES, which, in addition to summaries of Albertini's activities, include correspondence and reports. The notes provide extensive information on such subjects in modern French history as the war in Algeria, the May-June revolt of 1968, and rivalries among conservative politicians. The main focus of Albertini's political undertakings was to document the workings of the French Communist Party, and the notes contain detailed information on the finances, publications, and internal politics of the French C.P. Albertini was keen to counter what he perceived to be communist influence in other parts of the world, and there is a considerable amount of material in the papers relating to Latin America and Africa.
Albertini's sources of information included contacts within the French security services, and there are some reports emanating from the French political police, the Renseignements Généraux, in the chronological section of the NOTES, especially for 1968 and immediately after. There are also internal reports and minutes of meetings relating to the functioning of Albertini's research organization, the Centre d'Archives et de Documentation. These can be found in the topical section of the NOTES.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Communism--France.; Social history.; Communism.; Anti-communist movements.; France--Politics and government--20th century.
Collection Contents
- Biographical File, 1983-1986. (Box 1)
  Clippings and serial issue, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Clippings, 1983-1986 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Serial issue, 1983 (Folder 1: 2)
- Correspondence, 1938-1969. (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Unidentified, 1938-1943 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Allen, Richard V., 1969 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Buber-Faust, Margarete, 1949 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Laurat, Lucien, 1967 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Schueller, E., 1941 (Folder 1: 7)
- Writings, 1944-1945. (Box 1)
  Articles arranged chronologically
  - "Histoire du RNP (Rassemblement National Populaire)," 1944. (Folder 1: 8)
    Typescript
  - "Journal de prison," 1944-1945. (Folder 1: 9)
    Photocopy of holograph
- Notes, 1948-1979. (Box 1-16)
  Correspondence, dossiers, notes, and reports, arranged in two subseries, the first chronological and the second alphabetical by topic
  - Chronological
    - 1948 (Folder 1: 10)
    - 1949 (Folder 1: 11)
    - 1950 (Folder 1: 12)
    - 1951 (Folder 1: 13)
    - 1952
      - January-June (Folder 2: 1)
      - July-September (Folder 2: 2)
      - October-December (Folder 2: 3)
    - 1953
      - January-June (Folder 2: 4)
      - July-December (Folder 2: 5)
    - 1954
      - January-June (Folder 3: 1)
      - July-December (Folder 3: 2)
    - 1955
      - January-June (Folder 3: 3)
      - July-December (Folder 3: 4)
    - 1956
      - January-June (Folder 4: 1)
      - July-December (Folder 4: 2)
    - 1957
      - January-June (Folder 4: 3)
      - July-September (Folder 4: 4)
      - October-December (Folder 4: 5)
    - 1958
      - January-March (Folder 5: 1)
      - April-June (Folder 5: 2)
      - July-December (Folder 5: 3)
    - 1959
      - January-June (Folder 5: 4)
      - July-December (Folder 5: 5)
    - 1960 (Folder 6: 1)
    - 1961 (Folder 6: 2)
    - 1962 (Folder 6: 3)
    - 1963 (Folder 6: 4)
    - 1964 (Folder 6: 5)
    - 1965 (Folder 6: 6)
    - 1966 (Folder 6: 7)
    - 1967
      - January-June (Folder 6: 8)
      - July-December (Folder 6: 9)
    - 1968
      - January-June (Folder 7: 1)
      - July-December (Folder 7: 2)
    - 1969
      - January-June (Folder 7: 3)
      - July-December (Folder 7: 4)
    - 1970
      - January-March (Folder 7: 5)
      - April-December (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - 1971
      - January-June (Folder 8: 2)
      - July-December (Folder 8: 3)
    - 1972
      - January-June (Folder 8: 4)
      - July-December (Folder 8: 5)
    - 1973
      - January-June (Folder 9: 1)
      - July-December (Folder 9: 2)
    - 1974
      - January-June (Folder 9: 3)
      - July-December (Folder 9: 4)
    - 1975 (Folder 9: 5)
    - 1976 (Folder 9: 6)
    - 1977
      - January-April (Folder 10: 1)
      - May-August (Folder 10: 2)
      - September-December (Folder 10: 3)
    - 1978
      - January-April (Folder 10: 4)
      - May-August (Folder 10: 5)
      - September-December (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - 1979
      - January-April (Folder 11: 2)
      - May-August (Folder 11: 3)
      - September-December (Folder 11: 4)
  - Topical
    - Africa
      - 1958-1960 (Folder 11: 5)
      - 1961-1962 (Folder 12: 1)
      - 1963-1964 (Folder 12: 2)
      - 1965-1969 (Folder 12: 3)
      - 1970-1975 (Folder 12: 4)
    - Algeria
      - 1956-1957 (Folder 12: 5)
      - 1958-1959 (Box-folder 13: 1)
      - 1960-1962 (Folder 13: 2)
    - Baranès, André, 1954 (Folder 13: 3)
    - Brazil, 1967 (Folder 13: 4)
    - Catholic Church (France), 1969 (Folder 13: 5)
    - Centre d'Archives et de Documentation
      - 1948-1955 (Folder 13: 6)
      - 1956-1965 (Folder 13: 7)
      - 1966-1969 (Folder 13: 8)
    - Communist Party (France)
      - 1950-1951 (Folder 14: 1)
      - 1952 (Folder 14: 2)
      - 1953-1954 (Folder 14: 3)
      - 1958-1971 (Folder 14: 4)
    - France - Elections, 1956 (Folder 14: 5)
    - Italy - Politics and government, 1969-1970 (Folder 14: 6)
    - Soviet Union. Posol'stvo (France), 1958 (Folder 14: 7)
    - Latin America - Politics and government
      - 1961-1964 (Folder 15: 1)
      - 1965-1966 (Folder 15: 2)
      - 1967-1971 (Folder 15: 3)
    - Lecoeur, Auguste, 1954-1957 (Folder 15: 4)
    - Morocco - Politics and government, 1950-1951 (Folder 15: 5)
    - Naumann, Werner, 1952-1953. (Folder 15: 6)
      Includes typescript of "Les fossoyeurs sont parmi nous," a French translation of a series of articles by Fried Wesemann, 1953
    - Poland - Foreign relations - France, 1951 (Folder 15: 7)
    - Poujade, Pierre, 1956 (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - Socialist Party (France), 1956 (Folder 16: 2)
    - Soviet Union - Foreign relations, 1953 (Folder 16: 3)
    - Trade unions - France, 1972 (Folder 16: 4)
- Subject File, 1959-1967. (Box 16)
  Articles and book excerpts, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Banks and banking - Europe, 1967 (Folder 16: 5)
  - General Strike, France, 1936, 1966 (Folder 16: 6)
  - Mussolini, Benito, 1967 (Folder 16: 7)
  - Russia - History (1613-1917), 1959-1966 (Folder 16: 8)
  - Sorge, Richard, 1966 (Folder 16: 9)
  - Working class - History, 1966 (Folder 16: 10)
- Printed Matter, 1966-1967. (Box 16)
  Monograph and serial issues, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Monograph
    - Le parti communiste français en 1967, 1967 (Folder 16: 12)
  - Serial issues
    - Cahiers de l'histoire, no. 64, 1967 March (Folder 16: 12)
    - Cahiers libres, no. 93, 1966 December (Folder 16: 13)
    - Historiens et géographes, no. 200, 1966 October (Folder 16: 14)
    - Information historique, 1967 January-February (Folder 16: 15)